# **Md Rajib Hossen**

500 UTA Blvd #201, Arlington, Texas, 76013 (682) 367 3826 mdrajib.hossen@mavs.uta.edu www.linkedin.com/in/rajibhossen https://github.com/rajibhossen https://www.rajib-hossen.com/

**Expected Graduation: Dec 2023** 

#### **SUMMARY**

Ph.D. Candidate at the University of Texas at Arlington. Currently, I'm working on managing resources for microservices, identifying resource bottlenecks with a light-weight approach, and managing resource oversubscription in HPC Clusters. I'm looking forward to gain more research experience where I can apply my existing knowledge and learn new things to widen my research domain.

#### **EDUCATION**

# The University of Texas at Arlington | Arlington, TX

PH.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE | Supervisor: Dr. Mohammad A. Islam

• GPA: 4.0/4.0 | Relevant Courses: Advanced Algorithms; Machine Learning; Cloud Computing; Distributed Systems

## Khulna University of Engineering & Technology | Bangladesh

May 2015

**B.SC. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE** 

• GPA: 3.63/4.0 | Relevant Courses: Data Structure; Algorithms; Machine Learning; Data Mining

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- Md Rajib Hossen, Kishwar Ahmed, Mohammad Islam. 2023. Market Mechanism-Based User-in-the-Loop Scalable Power Oversubscription for HPC Systems. The 29th IEEE High-Performance Computer Architecture (HPCA 2023)
- Md Rajib Hossen, Mohammad Islam, Kishwar Ahmed. 2022. Practical Efficient Microservice Autoscaling with QoS Assurance. The 31st Symposium on High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing (HPDC 2022)
- Md Rajib Hossen, Mohammad Islam. 2022. Towards Efficient Microservices Management Through Opportunistic Resource Reduction. The 13<sup>th</sup> Conference on Cloud Computing, GRIDs, and Virtualization (Cloud Computing 2022)
- Md Rajib Hossen, Mohammad Islam. 2022. Practical Efficient Microservice Autoscaling. ACM International Conference on Measurement and Modeling of Computer Systems (SIGMETRICS 2022) (Poster)
- Md Rajib Hossen, Mohammad Islam. 2020. Mobile Task Offloading Under Unreliable Edge Performance. Workshop on AI in Networks and Distributed Systems (WAIN 2020, collocated with Performance'20) (Workshop)
- A. K. Paul, **M. R. Hossen**, B. Sarker and M. C. Urmi, "An approach to demand side load curtailment for the future intelligent and smart power grid of Bangladesh," 2014 International Conference on Electrical Engineering and Information & Communication Technology, 2014, pp. 1-7.

## **RESEARCH AND WORK EXPERIENCES**

#### Graduate Student Researcher | The University of Texas at Arlington | Arlington, TX

Aug 2018 - Cont.

- Reduced total CPU usages of microservices by more than 33% compared to state-of-the-art resource managers
- Develop novel algorithm to automatically optimize resources of microservices that works on top of kubernetes
- Identified bottleneck services using container and node metrices without violating Quality of Services
- Implemented several API microservices in Python, Go to deploy in Kubernetes environment
- Deployed a centralized monitoring environment (Grafana, InfluxDB) which gather system metrics as well as docker run-time metrics
- Decreased mobile task completion time with the same energy as greedy using intelligent mobile edge offloading
- Developed a system to address the power surge of power oversubscribed HPC clusters by incentivizing the users

## Software Engineer | Goava Sales Intelligence AB | Dhaka, Bangladesh

Jan 2018 - July 2018

- Accelerated development phase and conserved resources of the company by introducing APIs for providing personalized recommendations, custom filtering, and targeted companies for B2B
- Developed an API Server that provides results of queries from Elasticsearch and S3, and applies Machine Learning to satisfy client requirements

## Software Engineer | IPvision Soft Ltd | Dhaka, Bangladesh

Sep 2016 - Dec 2017

- Improved the efficiency of a cluster deployment of 50 Node by 75% using automation scripts in Python
- Reduced cloud computing cost by 83% compared with Amazon AWS by deploying a private cluster
- Incorporated a cloud dashboard using Django framework to provide monitoring for the private cluster using OpenStack, Ceph, GlusterFS, and custom API
- Wrote automation scripts in python to deploy private cloud using OpenStack, Ceph storage system integration, Hadoop Cluster deployment.

## Jr. Software Engineer | Workspace Infotech Ltd | Dhaka, Bangladesh

July 2015 - Aug 2016

- Delivered mobile application backend several weeks earlier than the deadline, boosted client's business
- Proven Adaptability in software development by working with back-end and front-end systems simultaneously

### **SKILLS**

- Programming Languages: Python, SQL, C++, Java
- Tools and Technologies: Kubernetes, Docker, Prometheus, Linux, AWS/Azure, Pytorch, Hadoop, Django

#### **AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS**

#### **HPDC'22 Student Travel Grant Award**

June 2022

Received NSF Travel Grant to attend the HPDC 2022 Conference in Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA

#### **I-Engage Mentorship Summer Research Grant**

June 2022 - Aug 2022

Office of Graduate School at UTA

• The I-Engage program by the graduate office offers doctoral students an opportunity to practice mentorship skills and exposes undergraduates to cutting-edge research in their field. We submitted a proposal to conduct research with an undergraduate student and got funding to continue the research.

## **Best Poster Awards (Honorable Mention)**

Feb 2022

Student Computing Research Festival (SCRF)@The University of Texas at Arlington

 Annual Student Computing Research Festival (SCRF) is an all-day event that allow students of any major to showcase their computing-related work in and out of classrooms, learn from professional role models, and engage with leaders of industry and society

## 2<sup>nd</sup> Place in Best App (Mobile and Desktop) Development

Mar 2014

App Development Hackathon by Dhaka University IT Societ

We achieved second place (among 50 teams) for developing an application within three days in a Hackathon

#### **Dean's List Award** Feb 2013 - May 2015

Khulna University of Engineering and Technology

• Dean's List Award for outstanding academic results (GPA > 3.75/4.0) for 2 consecutive years

#### **ACTIVITIES AND SERVICES**

## **Innovation Day Judge**

**Student Volunteer** 

**April 2022** 

Reviewed several posters submitted for annual showcase of research and innovation from Engineering Students

#### **Student Volunteer** Nov 2020

Volunteered at the ACM SIGPLAN conferences (OOPSLA, SPLASH)

Feb 2014

Volunteered at the 1st EICT Conference at Dhaka, Bangladesh

## President – Bangladesh Student Organization at University of Texas at Arlington

**Aug 2021 – July 2022** 

Lead student organization with 200+ members to arrange various cultural and sports events.

## **TEACHING ASSISTANT**

- Algorithm Analysis and Design: Fall and Spring of 2019, 2020, 2021, 2022
- Introduction to Computer Science: Summer of 2020, 2021
- Professional Practice: Summer 2022